Benjamin Tallmadge Collection
Litchfield Historical Society
Benjamin Tallmadge Collection
1777-1864
1778-1833
Litchfield Historical Society 7 South Street, P.O. Box 385 Litchfield, CT, 6759 URL: http://www.litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org/archon Email: archivist@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org Phone: 860-567-4501 Fax: 860-567-3565
Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835; Cushman, John P. (John Paine), 1784-1848; Tallmadge, Frederick A. (Frederick Augustus), 1792-1869
5.00
The Benjamin Tallmadge Collection documents the personal life and professional career of Colonel Benjamin Tallmadge through his correspondence as well as his legal, financial, and personal papers. An army officer, chief intelligence officer, and organizer of the Culper spy ring during the Revolutionary War, Tallmadge became a businessman and U.S. Representative from Connecticut in Congress after the war.
1933-19-0
Scope and Contents
The Benjamin Tallmadge Collection documents the personal life and professional career of Colonel Benjamin Tallmadge through his correspondence as well as his legal, financial, and personal papers. An army officer, chief intelligence officer, and organizer of the Culper spy ring during the Revolutionary War, Tallmadge became a businessman and U.S. Representative from Connecticut in Congress after the war.
The collection contains Tallmadge's duplicate original letters to George Washington concerning military operations and Tallmadge's operations of the secret service during the Revolutionary War. These letters record not only detailed summaries of battles, movements of troops, and requests for provisions, but also the activities of spies and communications of their intelligence. Many of the letters are written in cipher. Also included are two original letters from Washington to Tallmadge concerning military administration.
The letters also record Tallmadge's business activities after the war, especially in his correspondence with his son-in-law, John Paine Cushman, a lawyer in New York and, from 1817-1819, U. S. Representative of New York in Congress, whose advice and assistance Tallmadge frequently sought for his financial transactions.
In addition, legal documents, accounts, and bills and receipts illuminate Tallmadge's business ventures, especially his purchases and sales of land in Vermont, New York, Massachusetts, and Ohio, with references to the Ohio Company and Western Reserve. Other items include accounts for Tallmadge's store in Litchfield, Connecticut; receipts documenting his investment in privateering ships; and bills of sale for the purchase of slaves.
Moreover, his letters to Cushman reveal their opinions on national politics and government, especially during Cushman's own service in Congress. Meanwhile, his letters to his daughter, Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, document the religious revival movement in New England, in which Tallmadge took great interest, describing the activities of such revivalist preachers as Lyman Beecher, Asahel Nettleton, and Nathan Beman. These letters also provide insight into the social and personal activities of the Tallmadge and Cushman families in Litchfield and elsewhere. Occasionally, the letters are appended by notes to Maria from Tallmadge's second wife, Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge.
The collection also contains correspondence and business papers of Tallmadge's son, Frederick Augustus Tallmadge, which primarily concern Frederick Tallmadge's publication of his father's memoirs.
Arrangement of Materials
The collection is arranged in 5 series:
I. Correspondence
II. Legal papers
III. Financial papers
IV. Miscellany
V. Frederick A. Tallmadge papers
Related Materials
Mary Floyd Tallmadge Recipe Book, Litchfield Historical Society collection.
Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman Recipe Book, Litchfield Historical Society collection.
Connecticut Historical Society
Hartford, CT
Connecticut State Library
Hartford, CT
New York Historical Society
New York, NY
New York Public Library
New York, NY
Historical Society of Pennsylvania
Philadelphia, PA
Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery
San Marino, CA
Yale University Library
New Haven, CT
Separated Materials
Account books, diplomas, certificates, and military commissions are housed in oversize boxes.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Society of the Cincinnati
Genre/Form of Material:
Account books; Correspondence; Receipts
Geographic Name:
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Secret service; United States--Politics and government--1775-1783.; United States--Religious life and customs; Western Reserve (Ohio)
Personal Name:
Cushman, John P. (John Paine), 1784-1848; Cushman, Maria Tallmadge, 1790-1878; Deming, Julius, 1755-1830; Destouches, Charles-Rene´-Dominique Sochet, 1727-1794; Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817; Hooker, Asahel, 1762-1813; Reeve, Tapping, 1744-1823; Washington, George, 1732-1799
Topical Term:
Privateering--United States; Revivals--United States; Second Great Awakening; Slavery--Connecticut
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Custodial History
Descended in the family prior to donation to LHS.
Alternate Formats Available
Transcriptions are available for some documents.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Litchfield Historical Society from Mary Floyd Williams on 01/01/1933.
Accruals
Gifts from Emily Noyes Vanderpoel; Dorothy A. Johnson; Mary Floyd Tallmadge Seymour (1911); Elizabeth Delafield (1914); Morris W. Seymour (1917); L. J. Carrington (1923); Mary Floyd Williams (1942); White Memorial Foundation (1952); R. W. Belfit (1965); O. B. Swift (1971); Lynne Brickley (2004, 2005); and Malcolm and Carol Bramley (2005).
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements
A few originals are not available due to fragility. Use photocopy.
Other Information
Material objects at the Litchfield Historical Society relating to the Benjamin Tallmadge Collection include:
-2 portraits of Benjamin Tallmadge and Mary Floyd Tallmadge by Ralph Earl (1917-04-01, 1917-04-02)
-silver teaspoon (1907-02-14)
-silver tablespoons (1907-02-13, 1907-02-12, 1958-09-8)
-Chinese export porcelain coffee cup (1908-07-01)
-portrait miniature of Benjamin Tallmadge by John Ramage, 1783 (1986-17-1)
-silver tea service (1992-13-1 a-d)
-Benjamin Tallmadge & Co. trade sign (1971-06-0)
-oil painting of Benjamin Tallmadge by Ezra Amos, ca. 1825 (1974-09-1)
-oil painting of Maria (Hallett) Tallmadge by Ezra Amos, ca. 1825 (1974-09-2)
-hair cutting of Benjamin Tallmadge (1949-25-1)
-mourning pin with cutting of Benjamin Tallmadge's hair (ca 1910-01-19)
-silver salt spoon (1907-02-16)
-silver sugar tongs (1912-14-3)
-2 silver salt spoons (1912-14-4)
-silver mustard spoon (1907-02-15)
-large silver urn (1972-05-8)
Contact museum curator for further information at curator@litchfieldhistoricalsociety.org
This collection was processed with support from the Council on Library and Information Resources (CLIR).
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1776-1856
  Series 1, arranged chronologically, consists of letters from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington during the American Revolution, and letters among Tallmadge's family members after the war. The letters are fair copies in Tallmadge's hand.
  Tallmadge's letters to Washington document his military activities, as well as his activities as George Washington's chief intelligence officer and the organizer of the Culper spy ring. The collection also contains two original letters from George Washington to Tallmadge (in folders 12 and 18).
  After the war, Tallmadge's correspondence with his family members record his business activities as well as religious, political, and social news in Litchfield, New England, and Washington, D. C.
  - 1777 (Folder 1)
    1 letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, concerning the purchase of horses for the army.
  - 1778 Jan-Feb (Folder 2)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, concerning provisions. He expresses his concern over the scarcity of stables and hay for his regiment's horses as well as his difficulty finding lodging for his men, and discusses the purchase of breeches, boots, and swords.
  - 1778 Mar-May (Folder 3)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington. Discusses Colonel Elisha Sheldon's contract with Mr. Estey of Massachusetts to purchase leather breeches for the regiment; asks whether dragoons whose families suffer by means of their absence may be dismissed from service; and reports on the condition of the troops and laments their lack of supplies and cash.
  - 1778 Jun-Dec (Folder 4)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington. Complains about the regiment's lack of horses. Informs Washington of his failure to receive a letter from Culper, the code name for members of Tallmadge's espionage network, and discusses Culper's concern about secrecy.
  - 1779 Jan-Apr (Folder 5)
    One letter from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington reporting on Culper's intelligence; his expenses; an intrusion into Culper's room by two women living in his house; and his satisfaction with a vial of ink sent him by Washington.
  - 1779 May-Jun (Folder 6)
    Letter from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington reporting on the failure of the arrival of a letter from Culper, and on Colonel Elisha Sheldon's desire to obtain horses for his regiment.
  - 1779 Jul-Aug (Folder 7)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington. The first two letters concern correspondence with Culper, including several passages in code. The third letter concerns provisions of weapons and horses for the regiment.
  - 1779 Sep-Oct (Folder 8)
    Three letters from Benjamin Tallmadge to General Robert Howe and George Washington. The first letter describes his recent military expedition at Lloyd's Neck; in the next two letters, he reports on the drafting of soldiers and on the desertion and subsequent recapture and punishment of three soldiers.
  - 1779 Nov-Dec (Folder 9)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, reporting on Culper's intelligence.
  - 1780 Jan-Mar (Folder 10)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington and Colonel Samuel Webb, reporting on intelligence from Culper Jr. and asking that Captain Bull be excused from immediately joining the regiment, due to the imminent death of his wife.
  - 1780 Apr-May (Folder 11)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington. The letters discuss provisions for the regiment and intelligence reports from Culper Sr. and Culper Jr.
  - 1780 Jun-Jul (Folder 12)
    Three letters, two from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington and one from George Washington to Benjamin Tallmadge. The letters discuss troop movements and intelligence from the Culpers.
  - 1780 Aug-Dec (Folder 13)
    Three letters: two from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, describing the recent military engagement at Fort St. George, and one from Tallmadge to Captain David Edgar, giving him military instructions.
  - 1781 Jan-Apr (Folder 14)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, discussing military tactics, deserters, and an improved plan to safely convey secret dispatches from Culper.
  - 1781 May-Dec (Folder 15)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, discussing intelligence from Culper; the activities of prisoners; and the importance of procuring horses for the regiment.
  - 1782 Jan-Jun (Folder 16)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, discussing intelligence from Culper and referring to a letter from Silas Deane.
  - 1782 Jul-Sep (Folder 17)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, discussing additions to the secret intelligence network and recommending the conduct of Sergeant Elijah Churchill.
  - 1782 Oct-Dec (Folder 18)
    Five letters: Four from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington and one from George Washington to Benjamin Tallmadge. Tallmadge's letters report on a failed naval engagement off of Long Island and relaying secret intelligence reports.
    George Washington's letter concerns the capture of four refugees.
  - 1783 Jan (Folder 19)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, which describe his efforts to guard the coast near Greenfield; the desertion and return of Thomas Banks; the loss of a vessel to enemy ships; and the subsequent capture of enemy boats.
  - 1783 Feb (Folder 20)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington, reporting on his successful capture of an armed enemy vessel on the Long Island Sound. The letters also observe the illicit trading activity of enemy privateers on the Sound.
  - 1783 Mar (Folder 21)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington. In the first letter, Tallmadge reports on the confinement of Nathan Barnum, prisoner of war. The last two letters inform Washington of the peace treaty just concluded in Europe.
  - 1783 Apr-Dec (Folder 22)
    Two letters from Benjamin Tallmadge to George Washington. The first details financial compensation for Culper and others in the secret service network and concludes with Tallmadge's expressions of gratitude and respect for Washington's leadership during the war. The second instructs Washington on how to reach him after he has departed from Princetown.
  - 1793 (Folder 23)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Timothy Dwight, containing extensive reflections on the morals and piety of his upbringing and early life, on his religious values while in the military, and on his present religious views.
  - 1794 Jan-Jun (Folder 24)
    Business letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Nehemiah Hubbard, referring to a note against the painter Ralph Earl.
  - 1794 Jul-Dec (Folder 25)
    Letter, from Asahel Hooker to Benjamin Tallmadge, with religious advice for Tallmadge's difficult circumstances. The letter is accompanied by a note by Hooker expressing his hope that his counsel will be satisfactory to Tallmadge.
  - 1800 (Folder 26)
    Business letter from Benjamin Tallmadge to Peleg Coffin, treasurer of the state of Massachusetts, concerning payment of several notes for a sale of land. The folder also includes an engraved portrait of Tallmadge.
  - 1806 (Folder 27)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Julius Deming, discussing the purchase of a silver christening bowl for their church.
  - 1807 (Folder 28)
    Three letters: one from Tapping Reeve to Benjamin Tallmadge's daughter Maria; one from Tallmadge to Reeve; and one from Tallmadge to Maria. Reeve's letter to Maria reassure her about her decision to turn down an unwanted suitor, while Tallmadge's to Maria praises her for her newfound views on sin and salvation. He also mentions writing poetry, and encloses an Ode for Christmas. Reeve's letter to Maria was conserved in August 2009.
    Tallmadge's letter to Reeve thanks him for effecting the religious transformation in his daughter Maria and encourages him to visit Tallmdage's children more often in order to instill religious fervor in them.
  - 1808 (Folder 29)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to his daughter Maria, expressing his satisfaction with her decision to join the Church of Christ in Litchfield and providing further religious reflections. He also writes of his desire for Maria's brother and sister to follow in her religious zeal.
  - 1809 (Folder 30)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to his daughter Maria and to Governor John Treadwell of CT. To Maria, he writes of the difficulties his minority political party faces in Washington, including his efforts to defeat a bill to raise a standing army.
    Tallmadge's note to Treadwell indicates an enclosed letter to General Jedidiah Huntington on the subject of the militia.
  - 1812 (Folder 31)
    Two letters, from Tapping Reeve to Maria Cushman and from Benjamin Tallmadge and his wife to Joshua Huntington. In the first letter, Reeve provides religious reflections; informs Maria of a religious awakening taking place in Southberry and Middlebury; and expresses his best wishes for her on her recent marriage to John Paine Cushman.
    The letter from Benjamin and Maria Tallmadge expresses their condolences on the death of Joshua Huntington's daughter.
  - 1812 (fragile) (Folder 32)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Governor Roger Griswold, indicating his acceptance as a member of the thirteenth United States Congress.
  - 1813 (Folder 33)
    Letter, from Tapping Reeve to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. He mentions the pestilence in Litchfield and offers religious reflections.
  - 1814 (Folder 34)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to his son-in-law John Paine Cushman, and from Tapping Reeve to Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman.
    Tallmadge's letter includes social news and mentions monetary exchanges. Reeve's letter also contains social news, as well as information about the religious awakening in Litchfield and extensive religious reflections.
  - 1815 (Folder 35)
    Letter from Benjamin Tallmadge to his daughter Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman. Tallmadge expresses his gratitude at hearing of Maria's improved health and offers religious reflections.
  - 1816 Jan-Jun (Folder 36)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to his son-in-law John Paine Cushman, reporting on the religious awakening moving through Connecticut and Massachusetts and exhorting Cushman to open his heart to God.
  - 1816 Jul-Aug (Folder 37)
    Three letters: one from Benjamin Tallmadge's son William to his sister Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, another from Benjamin Tallmadge to his daughter Maria, and a third from Tallmadge to Captain Alden Partridge, superintendent of the Military Academy at West Point.
    In his letter to his sister, William Tallmadge describes his recent trip to the Netherlands and mentions falling in love with an English girl.
    Benjamin Tallmadge's letter to Maria expresses his joy at the influence of the religious revival on his daughter Harriot.
    Benjamin Tallmadge's letter to Captain Partridge introduces his son, George Washington Tallmadge, reviews his son's prior education, and expresses his hope that his son will flourish at the military academy at West Point.
  - 1816 Sep-Dec (Folder 38)
    Letter, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, reporting on the death of Rev. Lyman Beecher's first wife, Roxana (Foote) Beecher.
  - 1817 (Folder 39)
    Two letters to John Paine Cushman, one from Benjamin Tallmadge, Jr., and the other from Benjamin Tallmadge, Sr. The first letter requests Cushman's assistance, in his capacity as a delegate to Congress, to advance the interest of Tallmadge Jr.'s friend, a midshipman on the US Ship Washington named Mr. Whipple.
    In the second letter, Tallmadge Sr. reports social news, and expresses his distaste for another war, referring to the "Spanish patriots in South America."
  - 1818 Jan 1-Jan 15 (Folder 40)
    Three letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to Colonel John Tayloe and John Paine Cushman.
    Tallmadge's letter to Tayloe serves as a letter of introduction for Cushman. His letters to Cushman contain social news and political commentary, including an observation that the bill to aid indigent Revolutionary solders has not yet been passed.
  - 1818 Jan 16-31 (Folder 41)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge and William Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. Benjamin Tallmadge discusses Congressional business, including the case of John Anderson's attempted bribery of members of Congress, and updates Cushman on the activities and health of Cushman's young children.
    William Tallmadge's letter to Cushman mentions his search for employment.
  - 1818 Feb (Folder 42)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. The letters discuss political figures and news, including his dislike of the idea of pay attached to the brevet rank, his disappointment that Revolutionary War veterans have not received sufficient monetary compensation, and his hope for the passage of a national bankruptcy law. Tallmadge also mentions his and his wife's recent attack of influenza.
  - 1818 Mar (Folder 43)
    Five letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, primarily discussing Congressional and political business, including his disappointment that the bankruptcy bill may fail and the imminent adjournment of Congress. Tallmadge also mentions his plans to travel to New York with Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman to meet Cushman.
  - 1818 Apr-Nov (Folder 44)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. The first letters contains business and financial matters; the second letter discusses his son Benjamin's request for a furlough from the Navy and passes along social and religious news.
  - 1818 Dec (Folder 45)
    Four letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, which discuss both political and social matters. In one letter, he comments on the Congressional committee appointed to investigate the bank of the United States and expresses his certainty that the committee will discover a system of favoritism there. He also discusses, in detail, his hopes that Congress will investigate the institution at West Point, since he believes it is currently being run by a despot. Elsewhere, he hopes that Revolutionary War officers will receive financial compensation before they have all passed away, and reports on the activities of young Tallmadge.
  - 1819 Jan 1-Jan 15 (Folder 46)
    Three letters from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman, and one letter from J. T. Stoddard to Tallmadge. The letters from Tallmadge discuss financial matters, including the potential sale of land; political matters, including Tallmadge's approval of General Andrew Jackson; and religious matters: he relates the powerful effects of Rev. Lyman Beecher's recent sermon.
    The letter from Stoddard responds to Tallmadge's request for information on his own case against his debtors Campbell and Jenifer.
  - 1819 Jan 16-Jan 31 (Folder 47)
    Five letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. The letters discuss political matters, including the first Seminole War and General Andrew Jackson's conduct therein, and the exposure of corruption in the bank of the United States. Tallmadge also praises the religious revival led by Rev. Lyman Beecher and writes of the death of their relatives' child.
  - 1819 Feb (Folder 48)
    Two letters, one from George Washington Tallmadge to his sister Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman, and the other from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. George Washington Tallmadge's letter mentions his studies in French at West Point, his growing height, and his affection for Maria's young son.
    Benjamin Tallmadge's letter to Cushman deplores the perpetuation of slavery in the United States.
  - 1819 Mar-Dec (Folder 49)
    Three letters from Benjamin Tallmadge to Augustus Porter and to John Paine Cushman. Tallmadge's letter to Porter requests Porter's sales accounts for salt, in connection with Tallmadge's company, Tallmadge Smith & Co. To Cushman, Tallmadge asks advice concerning pursuing Porter for the sales account of salt, requests money to purchase stock in the Albany City Loan, and discusses a suit he is considering initiating against a debtor.
  - 1820 Jan-Feb (Folder 50)
    Two letters, from Benjamin Tallmadge to John Paine Cushman. The first letter continues the discussion of a suit against Tallmadge's debtor, Samuel Brown and mentions Maria (Tallmadge) Cushman's pregnancy. The second letter congratulates Cushman on the birth of a daughter, and is appended by a congratulatory note from Tallmadge's wife, Maria.
  - 1820 Mar-Jul (Folder 51)